this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet se radio is
brought to you by the I Triple E
Computer Society I Triple E software
magazine online at computer org slash
software digital ocean is the easiest
cloud platform to deploy manage and
scale applications of any size
removing infrastructure friction and
providing predictability so developers
and their teams can deploy faster and
focus on building software that
customers love digitalocean stands out
from the crowd due to its simplicity
high performance and has no billing
surprises join over 150,000 businesses
on digital ocean sign up with a 300
dollar infrastructure credit at t-- o.co
/ SC radio for software engineering
radio this is Robert bloomin day I am
joined by Bruce mom Jen Bruce is a
senior database architect for Postgres
prior to that he has held a number of
positions relating to post cars
development and advocacy and was an
adjunct professor at Drexel University
he lectures and presents widely on a
range of Postgres topics you can find
many of his slides at mom join us today
Bruce and I will be talking about
database query planning and optimization
Bruce welcome to software engineering
radio well great to be here thanks there
anything else you'd like our listeners
to know about you that I didn't cover
well I'm kind of a longtime er I've been
with Postgres for 22 years and I've been
with my current employee underpriced DB
for 12 years so I was one of the first
people to help start Postgres in
Internet development and obviously we've
been through a whole lot up to this
point and we're sort of in a very golden
age for Postgres and it's becoming very
popular so I stay very busy and it's an
exciting time to be involved with the
project it's great that you'll be
bringing that wealth of experience in
Postgres
to our discussion in order for us to
have a conversation about query planning
I want to cover some foundational
concepts and definitions starting with
what is a database query a database
query is a query that follows more or
less the SQL standard as a way of
requesting data from the database in a
structured way what does the client send
and what do they get back well the
client is typically sending usually
ASCII text which is a mix of keywords
and identifiers and character strings
and numbers and as a return and it's
obviously formatted based on the SQL
it's supported by the database and what
they get back is a structured result set
of rows and columns what are the steps
at a high level of the database performs
in order to return the results so the
database is first going to scan the SQL
text for identifiers and keywords
that's called lexing then it's going to
parse it once it's parsed it's going to
be loaded into it into an internal
structure the structure is going to go
through something called the rewriter
which handles things like views then it
goes the optimizer which is sort of the
brains of the system which determines
how to efficiently execute that query
and finally it goes to the executor
where the actual query is executed and
the result returned we're going to be
talking mostly about the step involved
in the optimizer but you say a little
bit about the output of the parser and
what type of internal structure does it
create so there there are actually two
different types of SQL commands
categories that Postgres handles one is
sort of a full ball a full-blown query
which has a lot of complexity to it and
it's what you're probably familiar with
if you think of the word the key where a
select query or an insert a query an
update query or delete query those are
full-blown query
and those get loaded into something
called a query structure aptly named and
those get passed to the rewriter the
optimizer the executor the second type
of output of the parser is for utility
commands things like drop table grant
revoke create index and those are
utility commands specific those again
are internal see structures and those go
to a separate section of the Optima
section of the system doesn't really
have an optimizer executed to it and and
those utility handle those utility
commands are handled you know obviously
in a specific way depending on the type
of command it is so let's focus on the
full-blown queries what are some of
things that make queries complex to
evaluate well you know there's a bunch
of things I mean first off as I said
before the the full-blown queries can be
selects but they could also be inserts
or updates or deletes so they all kind
of fall into the same category obviously
a delete is kind of like a select and a
delete an update is an update you know
is a select and an update so they kind
of all work together and on those type
of full-blown queries typically have the
ability to reference multiple tables to
join multiple tables together to have
complex where clauses that restrict what
rows are actually processed critters
group by ability which allows you to
sort of use aggregates with ease there's
a having clause there sorting
there's a limit clause for a bunch of
them so this kind of allows you to sort
of CAC on a whole bunch of modifiers to
those commands to really very precisely
explain exactly what type of query and
what type of output you want to perform
single query could have one or more of
these factors such as a where Clause
joins group by and the more of those you
have the more work there is for the
backend deliver the correct results yeah
there's no question about that I
we you know we're always looking at how
do you receive the command from the user
and how do you return that you know that
that requests in the most efficient way
possible but you're right the more
tables you join to the more aggregates
you have the more sorting you're doing
the more work the relational database
has to do you mentioned the term join go
into more detail about what is a join
well joins are probably one of the one
of the defining aspects of relational
systems it's really it really goes back
to the foundations of relational algebra
that you know academically represent a
foundation for relational systems so
what a join is it's it's really the
ability to take a table or relation
depending on what term you want to use
which is a set of rows and columns and
join it to another relation or another
table that's defined in the same
database so you have the ability to not
only have data in one table but you can
bring data from other tables together
with that table either as a way of
merging columns from the two tables
together of restricting certain rows
that happen to be joined to other tables
so it's sort of the atomization
of your problem space so instead of
dumping all of your data into one big
table the relational system is really
designed to break it up into pieces and
that joining process is really necessary
to kind of bring the big data back
together to give the Kuip of results and
and actions that the user requested okay
for example you dealing with a retail
application you've divided your tables
up to have users shipping addresses
shipping methods but in order to bring
all those back in one queried have to
join the user table to the address table
and maybe the shipping method table all
in one query would that be an example of
a join yes absolutely
you know the novice way the
relational way to do this would be to
have one table for every action for
every aspect of the system so you'd have
one row which represents an order and
you're repeating the customer name if
the customer orders multiple items
you're repeating the customer on every
row you're can be eating they're
repeating their address on every row
you're repeating all sorts of things if
you only had your data in one table and
that type of duplication that type of
redundancy makes reporting very
difficult management very difficult data
cleanliness very difficult referential
integrity kind of keeping a structure
around the database it becomes very
difficult so by breaking things up as
you describe your you're basically
atomizing the aspects of that retail
environment in two entities like
customer order item shipping address and
by atomizing those things the system
becomes much more efficient there's less
storage required your date is easier to
manage your data your data is easier to
update because you only have the
customer name in one place you only have
their shipping address in one place and
so forth so that's the way most of most
relational systems work and that's why
the joins are so important because even
though you've atomized everything you
still need to bring them together to do
useful work a relational model in order
to achieve this goal which it sounds a
lot like what software engineers called
don't repeat yourself you've carefully
isolated the data into these unique
tables and that creates the need to
merge everything back together in order
to answer many types of useful questions
that cannot be answered by a single
table yeah the fundamental beauty I
think of relational systems is that once
things have been atomized you can do all
sorts of very interesting
representations of that data so you're
not stuck with one table and one
representation that you happen to have
set up when you originally wrote the
application you could do something like
give me the ten oldest customers or the
five most recent orders or the
Geographic
the five closest shipping addresses and
then also give me the customer name and
by the way how many orders did they make
in the past six months and so forth so
by atomizing the data and then having
joints to bring them together you have
basically a lego set that allows you to
bring together your data in all sorts of
interesting and creative ways and I
think one of the great strengths of
relational systems and the reason
they've been around for so long is
because they have that flexibility to
effectively bring together data in all
sorts of computation contortions
whatever the business need is so when
you write your application you may have
only one need for that data but as we
may know from practical experience once
the data is in the system everyone wants
the app that data and they want to do
all sorts of interesting ways of using
that data and relational systems just
very good at that and the joins make
that type of flexibility almost seamless
to the application programmers the
database is working very hard to do all
sorts of very complex joins and
representations of that basic data but
the user merely has to type what they
want and the database goes and does it
Bruce we covered declarative programming
in episode 289 this sounds like what
you're talking about the user says what
they want and the system figures out how
to do it
sequel a good example of a declarative
programming technology yeah I would say
sequel is probably the most popular
declarative technology I can think of I
mean obviously there's a lot of
imperative languages you know Java and C
and Python and so forth where you tell
the system what to do but I would say
SQL is one of the few declarative cases
where you're actually telling the system
what you want and the system figures out
how to get it for you in the most
efficient way and I think that's kind of
kind of a neat aspect of SQL why is
declarative a good solution to the
problem posed by relational databases so
if you did not have the declarative
ability and SQL and and I I do go back
far enough to have have used pre SQL
databases the problem is that every time
you want to look at the data in a
different way you have to write a new
imperative program to do that so if I
want to look at join the data in a way
that I had not done before I'm rolling
up my sleeves and I'm writing a program
and if I want to do it a different way
I'm going to write another program so
the problem is that don't have the you
don't have sort of the efficiency of
being able to just write what I want and
let the fist system figure it out and
and for some reason when you write an
application normally people aren't
fiddling with the application 20
different ways yeah of course it goes
through iterations but normally
application stays pretty static from day
to day with SQL yeah there are
applications that pretty much Restonic
from day to day but but because a
business needs you're often doing ad hoc
queries all the time getting analytics
from the database doing new ways of sort
of slicing up the data and showing
what's happening organization and that
that just really lends itself to
declarative language where you don't
really have to write a program every
time you want the data in different way
you just have to declare what you want
in a different way and the database
engine basically gets abstracts a lot of
those problems away from the application
programmer and handles it at the data
layer which I think is a better place to
do that kind of particularly because
you're dealing with a lot of data that's
the the better place to be doing that
kind of optimization I'm trying to
imagine what this program would look
like if I wrote an imperative program I
have written programs that involve let's
say open up this set of files read a
bunch of records plot a field
now go query this API for each item
corresponding to one field and now open
the CSV file and so is that the kind of
imperative program that I would be
writing if I didn't have a declarative
query processing language yes absolutely
and and I've written those applications
they're not really fun they're kind of
they're kind of hard to do because
you're dragging a lot of the data to the
application right and you know the joins
are kind of awkward you you you
typically end up falling back as you're
saying to some type of a nested loop
join which is normally you know give me
the row go to the other table or the
other file and give me all the matches
and then get the next row and and do the
same thing but there's problems with
that first you're dragging all the data
to the client secondly there are other
join methods that are supported in
relational systems that typically aren't
written in application so you don't see
people writing merge joints or hash
joints very often in applications
because it's kind of hard and and and
people don't really think of it so they
end up to brute-forcing it so you end up
with very simplistic ways of joining the
data if you don't have a relational
system to do that but the third problem
which you might not realize is that is
that the relational system knows how
much data is in each table it knows how
restrictive these these conditions are
so it is constantly adjusting itself
based on what data is currently in the
system to give you the best answer even
if you wrote an application today and
you did this type of join and let's
suppose you actually we're really smart
and you wrote a hash join your row to
merge joint well the problem is that
that's gonna do whatever your program
specified for a joint type forever
whether the data changes or doesn't
change your application doesn't know
that it's just going to keep doing the
same thing one of the cool things about
relational systems is that they will
actually adjust live based on the data
they they have now not necessarily the
data that they had you know when the
query was written maybe a month ago and
that adaptability is something you
almost gets impossible almost to do an
application okay I think we've now
established what is the problem to be
solved and why you would like
to have a declarative model where you
hand it off to a back end in the back
end will figure it out for you so we're
kind of talking about this but tell me
what what is the query planning what is
a query plan so as I said before that
that query plan is that third stage of
the four stages of of the relational
system the first one is parsing the
second ones rewriting third one is the
optimizer which we also call the planner
and that outputs a query plan and the
query plan is what's fed into the
executor so plan a query plan is
effectively what the the database
software considers to be the optimal way
or the optimal set of instructions to
get you the data that you requested okay
so a creep planet consists of some set
of more primitive operations that will
achieve the result requested by the user
so if I looked at a query plan what
would I see you would see basically
elemental building blocks of
instructions that the executor needs to
process in order to complete that query
so you would see a mixture perhaps of a
sequential scan an index scan a sort a
hash join an aggregate operation a limit
there's all sorts of materialized view
these all sorts of actions that probably
a dozen or two dozen different types of
actions that you would see and it would
be set up in a tree environment where
you would you would say do this first
and then once that's done feed that
result into into a join or into an area
or into a sort and then after that's
done do something else until the query
was finished let's go back to this
retail example suppose a query is I want
to pull from a user's table and address
tables the users and the users primary
shipping address and get this all sorted
by zip code
what would
a possible query Plan B to execute that
query so what that would normally be
would be probably an index lookup if you
supply the customer name for example we
would do an index lookup on the customer
table we would get their identifier for
that customer the sequence number or
whatever however we uniquely identify
the customer then we would we would take
that number and we would join it to
another table for example the orders
table and we would sort of see all of
the open orders for that customer and
then we might also take that order ID
and go to the cost to the address table
and find the address for that customer
and there also we would look at the zip
code I mean we may limit on zip code so
for example if we want to see all the
customers it zip code we might do a
restriction which would say give me all
the addresses in the zip code and then
then go to see the customers that did
match that so that's an example of how
you might go one way you might go from
the customer to the address table or the
customer the order table you may go for
the address table to the customer table
depending on the type of query depending
on how much data is in each table
depending on the restrictions and the
where clause you're gonna do different
orders of joins depending on the query
that's applied I can see if I knew the
customer it would make sense to start
from the customer but as you described
there if you had three tables we know
there are ours the combinatorial number
of possibilities you could do starting
from the customer and then orders and
then addresses or any of the other
combinations how does the query planner
what is it looking at to decide which
combination of ordering is the best yes
that's a great question because you you
normally see the plan coming out but you
don't really understand how did it get
there how did it choose the instructions
that it chose and that's always been
fascinating to me to figure out exactly
why does the system do what it what it
does and when you do obviously when
you're working over on a proprietary
database you can't see
the source code but the post cuz you
can't so you can actually see how it's
choosing these things but effectively
when you're looking at these when you're
looking at the different options every
operation in the system whether it's a
limit or sword or join or an index scan
or a sequential scan has some type of
cost associated with it and what the
system will do is it will do a cursory
look at all the tables mentioned in that
query and it will look at the
restrictions the winter Clause
restrictions that are mentioned and will
try and it'll it'll actually cost out
which way will probably be cheapest and
then if it determines that one way is
cheapest it'll go that way if it thinks
in two ways maybe also equally cheap it
may actually carry both options through
the optimizer until at the end it
eliminates one of the two options so
you're right it is a factorial kind of
problem but there is a pruning process
that's happening as you're running
through the query and that pruning
process prevents the system from just
spending huge amounts of time you know
considering different plans okay you're
talking about costing these options out
and I do want to come back to that first
I want to get more detail about the term
scan which you've introduced so there's
two real there's probably two or three
fundamental ways of accessing data one
is to sequentially scan the entire table
we call that a schedule scan and it
sounds exactly where it is it basically
will sequentially read from the first
block to the last the entire table and
there are some queries that effectively
need a sequential scan if you're if
you're accessing a large portion of the
table to satisfy some query odds are
you're gonna need to read all the rows
to meet all it to all the pages and so
there are queries that will use
sequential scans there are other queries
where the queries much more focused it's
looking only for a specific customer or
a specific order number and in those
cases were much more likely to use an
index scan because we believe that
the index will allow us to get at the
roads we're interested in much more
efficiently than reading every row on
the table an index then it's a data
structure that allows you to access
given a row more efficiently right it's
basically a sort of a in index well I
guess yes an index on top of the table
that gives me rapid access to specific
rows that match specific criteria so I
might have an index on the table which
gets me specific customer numbers very
quickly or I might have an index that
gives me the you know customers in
specific States very quickly or whatever
specific order numbers very quickly so
you have the ability to sort of add
these quick access and methods on top of
tables and you can identify specify
which which columns or which piece of
data in that table you want to you know
you want to rapidly access I can see for
example if I am looking for customers
and addresses and I knew the customer
number or the customer name and had the
ability to access that through an index
could very quickly get that one row and
then proceed to the address table which
might have one or two addresses which
match that versus if I started with
addresses I would have to look at every
single address and then try to find
which ones match the customer so that
seems pretty obvious I would start from
customer in that case is that kind of
what the costing process looks like yeah
that's exactly what the costing process
looks like a system is gonna cost out
how you know how much how expensive is
gonna be to read every address right and
then it's gonna also cost out how
expensive is it going to be to read
every customer both sequential scans but
it's also gonna cost out using the index
and because you've supplied the customer
name and there is an index matching that
customer name that index access to the
customer table is way less much less
expensive
than the sequential scan of the customer
table or the sequential scan of the of
the address table so the system very
quickly discards the idea of doing
sequential scans on either of those
tables at least to get the customer and
it uses the index pretty quickly and
then it hopefully has once it gets the
customer number
there's hopefully another index on the
address table which will allow us to
pull the addresses up for that customer
ID very quickly if there's no index on
the customer table then the optimizer is
going to default to doing a sequential
scan which is of the address table which
effectively means it's gonna read every
single address looking for a matching
customer ID in that table we're talking
about cost then is it costing out how
long it thinks it will take to read data
off of some kind of storage device or
how does this cost translate into
something that the user cares about yeah
so the costing number is really only
meaningful to the extent that it's
cheaper than another costing number so
you can't really take the costing number
and extrapolate exactly how many
milliseconds it's gonna take to execute
the query it doesn't really work that
way cuz you're really mixing different
costs I mean there's a cost for aisle
access there's a cost for CPU usage
there's a cost for function call so you
have different costs that kind of all
kind of mashed together into a single
scale so the number that you see for the
cost is really not going to be
translated into any kind of meaningful
externally visible effect except to know
that an item with a cheaper cost is
probably most likely gonna run much
faster than one with a higher cost but
the numbers themselves don't really have
a physical meaning but the number
actually the a one for example means I
think it's the cost of a row access but
but again it's not that's not really
what you're going to care about when
you're trying to cost these things
you're really going to be looking at
which
is cheaper which cost is more expensive
and you're gonna do everything based on
that the costing then what reason do you
have to think that that cost will
translate into runtime or something that
the user perceives us better when you're
looking in the optimizer and you're
looking at different plans and different
ways of costing things you don't you
don't really care what the physical
representation that number is you just
want that you just want the plan with
the cheapest cost so if you have two
ways of getting at your data for example
one's an index scan wants a sequential
scan if one costs is less
that's the one we're gonna use whether
that cost represents twenty milliseconds
or forty milliseconds it doesn't matter
because the only thing you look at at
the end is the total cost amount you're
basically trying to to jumble a whole
bunch of options of how to get the
return the data to the user and you're
just trying to pick the cheapest option
it's kind of like going to a you know a
buffet and you're trying to pick the
cheapest amount of food you can get for
for dinner you're just really worried
about which one is cheap as the meaning
of the actual number isn't is never
really an issue digitalocean is the
easiest cloud platform to deploy manage
and scale applications of any size
removing infrastructure friction and
providing predictability so developers
and their teams can deploy faster and
focus on building software that
customers love digitalocean stands out
from the crowd due to its simplicity
high performance and has no billing
surprises join over 150,000 businesses
on digitalocean
sign up with a free hundred dollar
infrastructure credit at doco /se radio
I know that a database like postcards is
going to run an enormous range of
applications but in if there is such a
thing typical business applications how
many tables are we talking about that
could be in the median queries it one
two four twelve twenty will you know
that's a good question a lot of the sort
of olt
P which online transaction process the
typical order entry query you know it's
usually gonna hit three or four tables
you don't see you know maybe five or six
would be a big you know on the on the
high end of an OLTP type but traditional
transaction query mostly of those
queries are gonna really be looking for
a handful of rows like show me the order
you know put an order number in give me
the order detail or here's a customer
give me the addresses for that customer
right you're really talking about only a
handful of tables and you're normally
we're gonna return only handful of rows
when you start doing things like data
analytics then you start looking at a
lot of times you know fifteen twenty to
Abel's in some of these really big
queries because your data model is just
so humongous and you're you're you've
got so much data that you've atomized it
usually so discreetly that end up you
end up doing these huge amman and also
not only they have a lot of tables in
the query but you're also returning a
huge amount of rows so the optimizer has
to be very efficient and in fact when
you start to do a large number of tables
I think this is what you're alluding to
the system we can get very slow because
the optimizer all of a sudden has so
many ways of returning the data that it
actually the optimization time can
actually take a long a lot of time so
Postgres actually has something called a
GN a query optimizer which will randomly
sample plans and that allows you to take
a very big query that has a whole bunch
of tables and get a pretty good plan
without spending a huge - amount of time
on optimization questions here that are
related we were talking earlier about
this being a combinatorial size problem
exactly I don't know the value of six
combinatorial but I could imagine it
might be tractable where I'm I could
conceive of doing looking at six
combinatorial different plans and
picking the best one but I'm pretty sure
when you're getting in ten and twenty
that I can't look at every one you
talked about the pruning process where
you quickly eliminate a large number of
plans
my two related questions here how does
the optimizer narrow in on a few plans
and is there any thought given to how
much time can we spend planning where we
get to a point saying I'm just gonna go
with what we've got rather than spending
another hour planning to get you back
your 50 rows yeah that's absolutely true
so up until up until 12 tables Postgres
is going to try every option every
possible way of returning the data
meaning all the index scan options all
the sequential scan options but it's
gonna prune it as it goes so as it when
it's looking at a single table if it has
a pretty good index that is pretty
restrictive it's gonna it's going to
discard the sequential scan pretty
quickly it's not going to carry the
sequential scan through all the future
steps because it knows there is probably
no value to that sequential scan because
it has an index it's gonna be very good
if I'm asking for a given user we can
rule out I would never want to look at
every row in the user table I'm just
gonna use an index so we're gonna cost
it but we're gonna throw it away before
we get to the next stage okay because if
I don't if I carry that sequential scan
along then all the sudden the amount of
memory that I'm taking and the amount of
options I'm testing just becomes
overwhelming right so we are pruning it
as we're going in fact the the pruning
is one of the first optimizations that I
was involved in back in 1996 with the
optimizer and Tom Lane I kind of digged
into how it was working and pruned it I
did a lot of pruning stuff so you're not
carrying all those options through all
the stages if you did it would be
unbelievably slow but even if even with
all that pruning once you get beyond 12
tables even considering all of the ways
of accessing the data becomes expensive
so at 12 or more tables we're using
something called a genetic query
optimizer which is
basically randomly considering different
options of accessing the data it doesn't
even consider them all anymore because
even just kids it's much more aggressive
at pruning and particularly when you
start not so much pruning different
plans but when you get to twelve tables
even the the varieties of way you can
order by order the joints becomes huge
so what we end up doing there is we
randomly try different join orderings
until we find something that's pretty
good and then we just go with it because
you're right
it doesn't it doesn't make sense to
spend an hour optimizing a query if
you're only saving ten seconds in
execution time so you always have that
that holding over you is that every
minute the use every millisecond you're
spending and the optimizer you want that
to yield it over a millisecond in faster
query and when you start to get to these
very large tables that execute that
optimizer time could just be so big that
you basically throw up your hands and
you say you know we're not gonna get the
best plan here we're just gonna get one
that's good enough and go with it how
does it optimizer trade-off these
competing goals of avoiding a bad plan
finding a good enough plan and finding
the best plan well it's pretty much a
binary decision up until up until 12
tables we are gonna test all of the
possible joint options and prune them
and then everything over 12 tables we're
gonna randomly try different options and
just pick one that's the best of the
ones we've randomly chosen so you can
change that limit I mean you can
increase or decrease there are a couple
other things like collapse limits which
limits how much the how much the
optimizer is gonna try and collapse
things there are a couple optimizer
tunings that you can actually kind of
turn it on and off but it's not a great
you know it's not an exact science it's
kind of that number 12 we kind of came
up with that number from you know from
experimentation but I'm sure that there
are queries where it should be 14 and
there other queries it should be 10 and
and it's really hard to know when you're
Ronni you don't you don't know the
future right so you don't really know at
the time you're optimizing their query
how much you're really saving and
normally you don't see queries like
particularly in data warehousing you
know you see that you don't see the same
query twice so so you don't have really
a track record of knowing exactly how
good or bad it is the good news is that
normally you know this is such an exact
science that normally you're probably
gonna get the absolute perfect plan
you know maybe 70% of the time and but
you're gonna get really good plans like
98% of time right so there's a very
small number of players that are really
gonna be terrible even if it didn't do
the perfect job odds are you know okay
it's gonna be an extra ten milliseconds
but in little grand scheme of things you
probably did the best you're gonna do
and you just go with it I've looked at
query plans where the optimizer is
creating temporary tables when and why
does it make sense to do that so
sometimes the system will what we call
materialized sub data and that typically
happens when you're doing some kind of
data processing like you're maybe doing
an aggregate or you're doing a function
call and then you want to use that data
for some other operation like a join or
you know you need to sort it or
something like that so you end up sort
of creating the temporary so as you're
running the query you create sort of a
temporary instance of an intermediate
state of that data and then once you
have the intermediate state you can then
do things like place it in a hash so you
can do a hash join or maybe you know do
another area on it or sort it and then
do another operation so you do see
temporary results sets coming in
Postgres allows you to control that if
you use common table expressions
Postgres effectively creates a temporary
data set for each common table
expression and then when you at the
bottom query when you're joining the
common table expressions together you're
effectively joining these temporary
result sets together
and the optimizer because the
temperatures old sets can do all sorts
of things with it
that they can't necessarily do with the
base table because the result the
temporary table may have a lot fewer
rows in the main table it may have
outputs of functions or areas that the
main table just doesn't contain so you
need that intermediate result sometimes
to efficiently return there the right
answer this is something like in a
program an imperative program I have a
variable where I stick some result it's
not the final result of my function but
it's something I calculate along the way
to getting to that final result yes in
mathematics where you'll say you know
you know x equals something and y equals
something and then we're gonna use X or
somewhere else and then why be used
somewhere else and you're using these
variables in ternary as intermediate
results right in mathematics but that's
kind of familiar to people because those
numbers are scalars so they're their
single numbers what's interesting about
relational systems that these temporary
results are not scalars they're not even
vectors they're effectively matrices
rows and columns so they represent a
data set not really an atomic value and
that's the only real difference between
using temporary results in a query and
using you know scalar variables in
mathematical proofs and stuff I can see
why with aggregates and sorting that
would create some kind of constraint on
the planning because in order to sort
something you do need to have every
value that goes into the sort before you
can do this sort does that help or
constrain the optimizer when there's a
sort yeah so for example if you were if
you're taking a table and you select out
out of 20 rows from the table and then
you want to sort it well what you don't
want to do is to take the whole table
and sort it because you only want 20
rows it doesn't make sense to sort the
whole thing and then pull the 20 rows
out so you're gonna take the 20 rows
you're going to you may be using index
if you're lucky to pull those 20 rows
out
and you're gonna make a copy of them in
some type of temporary location
remember it's not an it's not a scaler
it's it's an it's a matrix it's a row
and column collection and it's gonna
represent the twenty rows and it's gonna
represent maybe not all the columns of
the table but only the columns that are
needed for that particular query so we
might not have referenced all of the
columns in the table we may only
reference a couple of them so we're
gonna we're gonna we're gonna have fewer
rows and we're probably gonna have fewer
columns right and that's gonna be
basically in memory or potentially with
a backing store to disk because the
results set may flush to disk because
it's too big to fit in memory and then
we're gonna sort that temporary result
which is much more efficient obviously
because as fewer columns add fewer rows
and that that's what the result we're
gonna turn to the user so that's a great
example of why you would want to create
a temporary result set to make sorting
or processing or whatever much more
efficient you are mentioning your
involvement in some work to improve the
optimizer by doing better pruning
hopefully the outcome of this work is
you would make the optimizer better but
with any software development you could
also introduce bugs or make something
worse what type of testing do you do on
the optimizer to detect and prevent that
you introduced regressions into the
optimizer itself yeah that is something
that is always it's always really
haunted us and you know we're not alone
it pretty much haunts all of the
relational systems whether they're open
source or proprietary because the
optimizer is an incredibly difficult
piece of software it's incredibly
difficult to test and you're right if
you introduce a bug it's a major problem
you could be turning wrong results you
could be doing things inefficiently and
so forth what's really nice about
Postgres and the reason we've been able
over these 22 years to to get Postgres
really on par if not better than than
the than the the proprietary databases
is because we have a very
close relationship with our user base so
when cause somebody comes to us and says
hey here's a query and it's not running
really well we're able to basically dig
into it figure it work with that user
within a 24 hour 48 hour period and
often develop a patch that they can test
to make sure that this fix has improved
the problem for them but we also
obviously have thousands of people who
are looking at that patch to make sure
it works the answer is that we really
don't have a great test suite and I
don't know of anybody who really does we
have a test suite but it's it's hard to
know because that piece of silver is so
complicated that you're that you're
actually exercising all of the possible
payers in that optimizer so a lot of it
falls back to the other people in the
development team who are eyeballing that
patch the people who were just watching
the email lists who were looking at and
the user who's gonna put that patch
often in production and test it and
because we're able to iterate so quickly
with the optimizer and frankly the
entire system the quality becomes very
high and I know with proprietary
databases because they don't have good
contact with the users because the user
interface between the users and the
optimizer developers is typically very
limited and because the release cycle is
very limited they often are terrified of
changing anything the optimizer and and
it you know it's it's probably good for
these other databases but it they're
really limited in how how great how good
they can improve it because everything
has a trade-off and unless you're in
constant contact with your users you
can't really make a lot of significant
changes I'd like to switch gears a bit
and talk about this more from the sequel
developer or software developer
standpoint I've used sequel and other
declarative languages like puppet
terraform first you think this is great
I say what I want the system figures out
I don't need to know how it does it but
then turns out you kind of do need to
know how it does it to what extent
should developers be looking at their
query plans or QA people or DBA
before they run a query on a production
system right so I think it really really
comes down to the quality of your
optimizer right obviously if the
optimizer was perfect then you'd never
need to look at it
but of course it never will be perfect
so we often have we just have to come
with that assumption that there going to
be some cases that's true of all
relational systems there gonna be some
cases the optimizer is not gonna handle
well that's just this par for the course
I know that one of the people one of the
large companies who converted from a
proprietary database to postgres had an
entire team in their organization and
their sole job was to study the query
plans of that proprietary database and I
kind of talked to them early on when
they were switching the Postgres and
they wanted to know how this team should
monitor Postgres and I said I don't know
and I'm not sure if you're going to need
to do that once you switch they did
switch those people really did not have
a useful purpose in the organization
they try to train some of them but a lot
of them are resistant to learning
Postgres and I think a lot of them left
the organization so there are some poor
some databases particularly proprietary
ones that probably need steady
monitoring of their query plans
Postgres optimizer is pretty good not
perfect but pretty good and you don't
see a lot of that regular monitoring I
will tell you for example that when I
give a talk about the optimizer last
time I did in fact somebody said how can
i lock a plan how can I force a plan to
be static so it doesn't change and I'm
like why would you want to do that and
they're like well no I was like let me
guess you're not using Postgres right
now but you're doing this locking with
your current database and you think
you're gonna need to do with the
Postgres is that correct they said yeah
I said well I said you're probably not
gonna need to do that in Postgres so let
me know if you switch to Postgres and
you find you need to and nobody's ever
come to me say they need to there are
cases where it doesn't work and you do
need to study it there is a
called explain and if you type explain
and select or explain an update or
explaining delete or explain an update
it'll actually show you the query plan
and you can study it there's some
websites that allow you to analyze that
query plan you can look for cases where
the system miss estimated the number of
rows for example maybe a phone who's
gonna get a hundred rows and it got ten
thousand rows that would be an
indication that something is amiss
either in the statistics or in the data
layout or or maybe the function that was
to find it in an odd way but there are
things you can do to control the
optimizer if you find that it's not
executing very well your response you
focus on one source of poor performance
which could be that there is the
optimizer did a poor job but in an
organization a system a lot of things
could go wrong maybe the postcodes
optimizer does a brilliant job but the
table doesn't have the right indexes or
the amount of rows in this table has
grown and so you could end up with a
poorly performing query even though the
query planner did the best it could
given the information it had so my
questions a little more on do you think
development organizations should have
some kind of controls or QA procedures
to prevent poorly performing queries
however they originate yeah that's
that's a great point because there are
there are cases where we're doing a
sequential scan that where an index game
would be very helpful there are other
cases where people are creating indexes
that have no use and therefore they're
slowing the system down so it's actually
you can go both directions with indexes
basically yeah we have some some tooling
around that one is PG stat statements
which will actually show you another one
is called PG badger which actually gives
your report and it shows you which
queries you're taking a long time which
queries are run alot and taking a long
time so if your system is slow a lot of
times you're gonna start looking at
which queries you're taking up the most
amount of time maybe maybe they're
taking each queries taking a long amount
of time or a query may taking a short
amount of time but it's run so many
times that it's total execution
[Music]
all of them is very high and those are
the queries you're gonna want to look at
first to make sure again you're right
that the indexes that you need are in
place that the statistics are being used
properly and so forth in that's your
right that's the kind of thing that
people definitely should be monitoring
to make sure that their that their
queries are probably as good as they're
gonna get you're talking about a
iterative process where people will look
at these query plans and and you might
notice hey we're doing a table scan of
the user table on zip code we should
really add an index to that table on zip
code and that will improve the
performance of that query quite a lot
I'm wondering does a query planner or
any of your tools have the ability to
consider hypothetical query plans which
would come about by adding indexes that
don't exist and compare those to the
query plans that it has and maybe this
would be a separate report but tell the
user hey Bruce you might want to add
this or that index which will have a big
impact on some of your queries yeah
there is there is an extension you could
install in Postgres
which will allow you to create
hypothetical indexes and then run
explain assuming those indexes actually
existed and that allows you to kind of
do that kind of brainstorming to see if
the index actually would be helpful now
I want to move in a little bit different
direction talk about how you might apply
some of these concepts to a different
problem domain their massive popularity
of sequel has created a huge pool of
talent in this area who have sequel
skills but the choice of data sources is
becoming larger more heterogeneous all
the time so most what we might loosely
call databases have some kind of a
sequel like API for example there's
sequel type layers on top of Hadoop and
instead of compiling down into index
scans and row scans on file blocks it
generates jobs that run on a Hadoop
cluster if you were given a problem as a
problem to solve
like how it
create a good back-end for a Hadoop
cluster from sequel queries how would
you approach that problem how is it
similar or different to the problems you
worked on it with post Chris you know
it's it's I can give you a short answer
and an odd answer I mean the short
answer for that particular problem
domain is that I'd optimizer is
incredibly complicated and has decades
of sort of smarts in it it would be very
hard to kind of from scratch what the
optimizer is doing for Postgres is it's
taking a request for data it's looking
at the primitive building blocks it has
sequentially an index can different hash
methods different ideas sorting limits
and so forth I have in clause at where
clause and then it's kind of spitting
out a set of building blocks that
matches the request and if you were to
do that for a newb it's the same problem
although your building blocks underneath
it as you stated or different so you'd
you'd basically have to take the same
kind of process of parsing and and then
optimizing and it's but instead of
spitting out Postgres capabilities you
spit out the dupe commands you know that
would the and you obviously have to
optimize it for the type of things as
well like parallel processing one
interesting aspect of Postgres is the
fact that it supports over a hundred
different foreign data wrappers so you
can create a table in Postgres which is
literally a Hadoop cluster and therefore
when you access that table the post rest
foreign data wrapper effectively sends
instructions to Hadoop the dupe returns
the results the Postgres Postgres thinks
it's a local table and then it does all
of its joins higher hashes IRA gets and
and window functions on that Hadoop
result you see that a lot actually so
people who are mixing Hadoop data with
with data with Cassandra and then
maybe a call data recorder over in the
corner and then they're mixing that with
relational data in Postgres either
whether to do transactional operations
or analytics or
serve web pages with header key
data so it's kind of interesting
Postgres will effectively spit out the
part of the query that relates to that
specific foreign data source and send
that foreign data source to the foreign
data server and then wait for the result
and then combine it with other foreign
data sources or native Postgres data
this is reminding me of the earlier
example where we were talking about I
have a program and it needs to find a
bunch of rows based on some criteria
from this batch of files that API these
emails and if I could just Express what
I want rather than write this program my
life would be a bit simpler so it's a
way the postcards provides that
capability to you if you're willing to
write one of these wrappers so the
interesting before but the wrapper is
there's again over a hundred of them and
you just need to install the wrapper
you're not having to write any commands
to do Postgres automatically understands
which part of the of the query that you
sent us relates to that Hadoop cluster
and then sends the you know Hadoop
specific commands to that do cluster
gets the data back but then you're
you're back to the Postgres optimizer
and you have all the joins and you have
all that area you have all the other
cool stuff and that's actually a really
really popular use for Postgres is sort
of as a sort of as a data broker or a
sort of central data repository that can
talk to all these things but also has
thus parts of a relational system to
bring all that data together in a
seamless way yeah I can see that being
very useful Bruce we've covered pretty
much everything I wanted to talk about
is there anything else that you want to
cover we haven't talked about yet no I
you know I I really just love this topic
the this sort of understanding how that
declarative SQL language is interpreted
by the optimizer and generating an
optimal plan has always fascinated me
it's one of the reasons I got involved
Postgres early on having used a lot of
proprietary relational databases and
really curious how does it work how does
it do what it does what how can you in
fluence it how does it seem to know how
much data is in every table and how
restrictive things are and which indexes
should be used and which indexes
shouldn't be used I think it's a really
really fascinating topic and may again
maybe it's just me
you know it's an odd maybe it's an odd
thing to find interesting but every time
I talk about it every time I studied I
find it it's just a new way of seeing
you know software being used I think in
a very powerful way I'm aware of
Postgres my sequels the other
open-source database I can think of I
know there are people who work on these
issues commercial database vendors is
there a large research community around
this set of topics and is there a shared
body of knowledge that everyone in the
optimizer community is contributing to
you know I would love to say yes but I'm
afraid the answers probably no I've
attended one I Triple E conference where
we talked about some of the some of the
sort of optimizer issues and database
issues that that are kind of common
problem spaces but you know every
relational system has a different set of
of tooling and a different set of
primitives that that it supports you
know at the low level so a lot of the
problems that we're talking about in
terms of joins in terms of query
planning I mean these are these are
topics that have been studied for thirty
years it may be more a lot of them so
the body of knowledge is is pretty
static there's not a whole lot of new
stuff that comes out it's a pretty basic
I mean there are people who are looking
at stuff like okay how can we do spatial
better how can we do some you know some
of the new data types like they may be
JSON how can we do a better job of that
but the research community has tendency
to look at things very abstractly but
you know when we're actually working on
Postgres we need a practical answer and
a lot of the solutions we come up with
are homegrown you know we will read a
couple papers we'll sort of see what
what people have talked about but when
you finally get to the actual you know
code it's kind of a mishmash of oh this
was matching this paper and this
person in Russia had this idea and
somebody over in Germany like this and
Japan thinks it should be this way and
so it ends up being sort of a mishmash
of research and and practitioners
together really sort of dictating for
the the solution that comes out
digitalocean is the easiest cloud
platform to deploy manage and scale
applications of any size removing
infrastructure friction and providing
predictability so developers and their
teams can deploy faster and focus on
building software that customers love
digitalocean stands out from the crowd
due to its simplicity high performance
and has no billing surprises join over
150,000 businesses on digitalocean
sign up with a three hundred dollar
infrastructure credit at t-- o.co slash
SE radio okay now we've really covered
everything I wanted to cover to go into
the wrap up we talked about your website
mom Gen dot us there's the post cards
website there any other either personal
sources or websites you'd like to direct
our listeners tubers I think those are
the those are the big ones obviously the
community website has a huge email
community that's always talking about
Postgres and answering problems and I'm
sort of researching new features and and
sort of helping people to use Postgres
more efficiently there's a there's a
very big IRC channel there's a you know
the it's we're big on on a lot of the
big social media sites so we're kind of
all over now you know there's a time
when we were we were kind of kind of
small but that's that's times kind of
over so you can probably pretty much
find us everywhere but I think those are
probably the two there is a developer's
an FAQ that might be used for some
people there's a lot of presentations on
my website including recordings of a lot
of those so if there's things that
particular topics people are interested
in that might be a nice thing we have a
lot of conferences coming up so if
somebody would like to actually go and
talk to other Postgres people and spend
time with them and and hear you know
topics that might be interesting to them
we seem to have one or two conferences
every month around the world
so pretty much no matter where you are
there's something close to you related
to Postgres and those are also listed on
the Postgres website bruce mom Jen thank
you very much for speaking to software
engineering radio and for software
engineering radio this has been Robert
blumen thanks for listening to Nessie
radio an educational program brought to
you by Triple E software magazine for
more about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website at Etsy -
radio net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter
or through our slack channel at SC
radio.com
you can also email us at team @ SC -
radio net this and all other episodes of
SU radio is licensed under Creative
Commons license 2.5 thanks for listening